Types of Galaxies:


I. Spiral - flat, rotating disc; contains stars, gas and dust. Stars form a (usually two-armed) spiral structure and there is a central concentration of stars called the bulge. The bulge is surrounded by a much fainter halo of stars, many of which are contained in globular clusters. They are given the symbol "S" in the Hubble sequence.

	Main Subcategories:
	
	A. Barred - a spiral galaxy with a central bar-shaped structure composed of stars. Bars found in ~2/3 of all spiral galaxies.
		    Bars generally affect the motions of stars and intersetellar gas in spiral galaxies and can affect spiral arms. They
		    are labeled "SB" in the Hubble sequence, with 3 subcategories based on how open the arms of the spiral are (SBa having
		    tightly bound arms and SBc having loosely bound arms).

		Example: M95  -- Other names / type: NGC 3351 / SB(r)b
     				 Coordinates: 10h 43m 57.7s, +11° 42′ 14″ 
				 Distance: 32.6 ± 1.4 Mly
				 General Area: constellation Leo (part of trio of Leo w/ M96 and M105)
				 Size: about 75,000 ly in diameter, ~50 billion M☉, Apparent Mag 11.4
				 Wavelength: redshift 778 ± 4 km/s
				 Notable features: A Type II supernova, 2012aw, was discovered in M95 on 16 March 2012

	
	B. Unbarred - a spiral galaxy without a central bar, or one that is not a barred spiral galaxy; labeled "SA" in Hubble sequence

		Example: Sombrero Galaxy -- Other names / type: M104, NGC 459 / SA(s)a
     				            Coordinates:  12h 39m 59.4s, −11° 37′ 23″
				 	    Distance: 29.3 ± 1.6 Mly
					    General Area: can be seen w/ a small telescope towards the constellation of Virgo
				 	    Size: 50,000 ly in diameter, ~1 billion M☉, Apparent Mag 8.98 
				 	    Wavelength: redshift 0.003416 ± 0.00001
				 	    Notable features: central supermassive black hole, large bulge, dust lanes, very bright, very old 
				 		             (~13 billion years, very near estimated age of universe)

	
	C. Intermediate - a spiral galaxy that is in between classifications of a barred and an unbarred spiral galaxy. Designated "SAB" in
			  the galaxy morphological classification (Hubble Sequence)

		Example: Sculptor Galaxy -- Other names / type: Silver Coin or Silver Dollar Galaxy, NGC 253 / SAB(s)c
     				            Coordinates: 00h 47m 33s, −25° 17′ 18″
				  	    Distance: 11.4 ± 0.7 Mly
				 	    General Area: constellation Sculptor
					    Size: about 70,000 ly in diameter, ~100 billion M☉, Apparent Mag 8.0
					    Wavelength: redshift 0.000811
					    Notable features: The Sculptor Galaxy is a starburst galaxy, which means that it is currently       					    		      undergoing a period of intense star formation.

	D. Flocculent - Unlike the well defined spiral architecture of a grand design galaxy, flocculent galaxies are patchy, with 					discontinuous spiral arms. Approximately 30% of spirals are flocculent, 10% are grand design, rest are "multi-armed".

		Example: Pinwheel Galaxy -- Other names / type: M101, NGC 5457 / SAB(rs)cd
     				            Coordinates: 14h 03m 12.6s, +54° 20′ 57″
				  	    Distance: 20.9 ± 1.8 Mly
				 	    General Area: constellation Ursa Major
					    Size: about 170,000 ly in diameter, ~1000 billion M☉, Apparent Mag 7.86
					    Wavelength: redshift 0.000804
					    Notable features: On February 28, 2006, NASA and the ESA released a very detailed image of the 							      	      Pinwheel Galaxy, which was the largest and most detailed image of a galaxy by 							     	      Hubble Space Telescope at the time. The image was composed from 51 individual 							     	      exposures, plus some extra ground-based photos.



II. Irregular - does not have a distinct regular shape, unlike a spiral or an elliptical galaxy. The shape of an irregular galaxy is uncommon – they do not fall into any of the regular classes of the Hubble sequence, and they are often chaotic in appearance, with neither a nuclear bulge nor any trace of spiral arm structure. Collectively they are thought to make up about a quarter of all galaxies. Most irregular galaxies were once spiral or elliptical galaxies but were deformed by disorders in gravitational pull. Irregular galaxies may contain abundant amounts of gas and dust.


	A. Irr I - an irregular galaxy that features some structure but not enough to place it cleanly into the Hubble sequence. De Vaucouleurs 		   subtypes this into galaxies that have some spiral structure Sm, and those that do not Im.

		Example: Large Magellanic Cloud  --  type: SB(s)m
     				 		     Coordinates: 05h 23m 34.5s, −69° 45′ 22″
				 		     Distance: 162.98 kly 
				 		     General Area: constellation Dorado/Mensa; satellite of the Milky Way
				 		     Size: about 14,000 ly in diameter, ~10 billion M☉, Apparent mag 0.9
				 		     Wavelength: faintly visible in night sky
				 	Notable features: While the LMC is often considered an irregular type galaxy (the NASA Extragalactic 							  	  Database lists the Hubble sequence type as Irr/SB(s)m), the LMC contains a very 							  	  prominent bar in its center, suggesting that it may have previously been a barred 							 	  spiral galaxy. The LMC's irregular appearance is possibly the result of tidal 							  	  interactions with both the Milky Way and the Small Magellanic Cloud (SMC).

	B. Irr II - an irregular galaxy that does not appear to feature any structure that can place it into the Hubble sequence.

		Example: NGC 1427A  --  type: IB(s)m
     				 	Coordinates: 3h 40m 9.3s, −35° 37′ 28″ 
				 	Distance: 51.9 ± 5.0 Mly
				 	General Area: constellation Eridanus
				 	Size: about 30,700 ly in diameter, Apparent mag 13.4
				 	Wavelength: redshift 2028 ± 1 km/s
				 	Notable features: It is the brightest irregular member of the Fornax cluster and is in the 							  		  foreground of the cluster's central galaxy NGC 1399.

	C. Dwarf- labelled as dI or dIrrs, now thought to be important to understand the overall evolution of galaxies, as they tend to have a 		  	  low level of metallicity and relatively high levels of gas, and are thought to be similar to the earliest galaxies that 	  	  	  populated the Universe. They may represent a local (and therefore more recent) version of the faint blue galaxies known to 		 	  exist in deep field galaxy surveys.

		Example: Small Magellanic Cloud  --  type: IB(s)m
     				 		     Coordinates: 00h 52m 44.8s, −72° 49′ 43″
				 		     Distance: 197 ± 9 kly
				 		     General Area: constellation Tucana; member of Local Group
				 		     Size: about 7,000 ly in diameter, ~6.5 billion M☉, Apparent mag 2.7
				 		     Wavelength: redshift 158 ± 4 km/s
				 		     Notable features: Some speculate that the SMC was once a barred spiral galaxy that was 									       disrupted by the Milky Way to become somewhat irregular. It contains a 								       	       central bar structure.



*Between II and III* Lenticular - type of galaxy which is intermediate between an elliptical galaxy and a spiral galaxy in galaxy morphological classification schemes. Lenticular galaxies are disc galaxies (like spiral galaxies) which have used up or lost most of their interstellar matter and therefore have very little ongoing star formation. They may retain significant dust in their disks. As a result, they consist mainly of aging stars (like elliptical galaxies).

	Example: Spindle Galaxy  -- Other names / type: NGC 5866, M102 / S0
     				    Coordinates: 15h 06m 29.5s, +55° 45′ 48″ 
				    Distance: 50 ± 3 Mly
				    General Area: constellation Draco
				    Size: about 60,000 ly in diameter, Apparent Mag 10.7
				    Wavelength: redshift 672 ± 9 km/s
				    Notable features: contains the nearest billion-solar-mass black hole to Earth.


III. Elliptical - type of galaxy having an approximately ellipsoidal shape and a smooth, nearly featureless brightness profile. Unlike flat spiral galaxies with organization and structure, they are more three-dimensional, without much structure, and their stars are in somewhat random orbits around the center. Stars found inside of elliptical galaxies are very much older than stars found in spiral galaxies. Ellipticals are classified by their shape,The number is given by 10x(1-b/a) where b = the apparent size of the short axis and a = the apparent size of the long axis.E0 is the most spherical, E3 is most common shape, limit is about E7. 
	
	
	A. Dwarf -  elliptical galaxies that are much smaller than others. They are classified as dE, and are quite common in galaxy groups and 		    clusters, and are usually companions to other galaxies.

		Example: M32  -- Other names / type: NGC 221, Le Gentil / cE2
     				    Coordinates: 00h 42m 41.8s, 40° 51′ 55″ 
				    Distance: 2.49 ± 0.08 Mly
				    General Area: constellation Andromeda
				    Size: about 5,000 ly in diameter, ~3 billion M☉, Apparent Mag 8.08
				    Wavelength: redshift -200 ± 6 km/s
				    Notable features: satellite galaxy of Andromeda Galaxy (M31) and was discovered by Le Gentil in 1749.

	B. E0-E2 Ellipiticals

		Example: M105  -- Other names / type: NGC 3379 / E1
     				    Coordinates: 10h 47m 49.6s, +12° 34′ 54″
				    Distance: 32.0 ± 1.6 Mly
				    General Area: constellation Leo
				    Size: ~100 billion M☉, Apparent Mag 10.2
				    Wavelength: redshift 911 ± 2 km/s
				    Notable features: Messier 105 is known to have a supermassive black hole whose mass is estimated to be 						      between 1.4·108 and 2·108 solar masses. It also contains a few young stars and stellar 						      	      clusters, suggesting some elliptical galaxies still form new stars, but very slowly.

	C. E3 Elliptical

		Example: IC 1101 -- type: E3 (Supergiant)
			            Coordinates: 15h 10m 56.1s, +05° 44′ 41″
				    Distance: 1.07 Gly
				    General Area: Virgo 
				    Size: ~2,500,000 billion M☉, diameter of 6,000,000 ly, Apparent Mag 14.7
				    Wavelength: Redshift 23370 ± 30 km/s
				    Notable Features: The galaxy is classified as a supergiant elliptical (E) to lenticular (S0) and is the 							      brightest galaxy in A2029; massive black hole source, golden yellow in color from metal-						     	      rich stars

	D. E5-E7 Ellipticals

		Example: Centaurus A -- other name / type: NGC 5128 / S0 pec or Ep
			                Coordinates: 13h 25m 27.6s, −43° 01′ 09″
				        Distance: 10–16 Mly
				        General Area: Centaurus constellation
				        Size: ~1,000 billion M☉, Apparent Mag 6.84
				        Wavelength: Redshift 547 ± 5 km/s
				        Notable Features: There is considerable debate in the literature regarding the galaxy's fundamental 							  	  properties such as its Hubble type (lenticular galaxy or a giant elliptical galaxy; 							  fifth brightest galaxy in the sky, contains a supermassive black hole with a mass 								  equivalent to 55 million solar masses, which ejects a relativistic jet that is   							  responsible for emissions in the X-ray and radio wavelengths (starbust)
	
	 





			
						  
